<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King and Queen, a proclamation concerning coals</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1689-1694 : William and Mary)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2557</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40703</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19525186</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19525186</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108965</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108965)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1679:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King and Queen, a proclamation concerning coals</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1689-1694 : William and Mary)</author>
                  <author>William, III, King of England, 1650-1702.</author>
                  <author>Mary II, Queen of England, 1662-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Charles Bill, and the executrix of Thomas Newcomb ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Given at our court at Whitehall, the twenty third day of April, 1691, in the third year of our reign."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Coal trade --  England.</term>
               <term>Proclamations --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:108965:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>W R M R</head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               </figure> By the King and Queen, A PROCLAMATION Concerning COALS.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>WILLIAM R.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas an Act of Parliament was lately made for Regulating the Prices of Coals, and Supplying the Navigation of the Coal-Trade; And in purſuance of the ſame, Our Lord Mayor and Aldermen of Our City of <hi>London,</hi> and Our Iuſtices of Peace of Our County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> and City of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> have acted with great Induſtry, Care and Prudence, by Settling and Moderating the Prices of Coals, and Providing by good and diſcreét Means for the Relief of Our People, Inhabiting in, and about thoſe Places, (of whoſe Performance and good Service in the Premiſſes We do highly Approve.) Yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs there hath happened lately a great Scarcity and Dearth of Coals, occaſion'd part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by divers Colliers ſtaying Part, or by the Way with their loaden Veſſels, during ſuch time as the Wind ſerved, and was proper for their Sailing, and partly by the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, or fear of Preſſing of their Seamen, to Serve on Board Our Ships of War, and alſo the Neglects or Miſcarriages of ſome Officers imployed for Convoys. Now in tender Compaſſion and Care for Our good Subjects, being earneſtly deſirous to do all that in Vs lieth for providing againſt any Want or Diſtreſs, likely to befall them on this Occaſion, We have thought fit, by and with the Advice of Our Privy Council, to Iſſue our this Our Royal Proclamation, and do hereby Declare and Command, That no Seaman, either <hi>Engliſh</hi> or Foreigner, that ſhall be Imployed in any Ship or Veſſel, Bringing or Carrying Coals from Our Town or Port of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> upon <hi>Tine,</hi> or <hi>Sunderland,</hi> or other Adjacent Ports or Places unto Our Port of <hi>London,</hi> ſhall be Preſſed or otherwiſe Hindred or Moleſted, either coming or Returning, by any of Our Preſs Maſters, or other Officers or Miniſters, until the Twentieth Day of <hi>July</hi> next. (So as the Seamen Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed on Board ſuch reſpective Ship or Veſſel, do not exceéd the Number of Four Men for every Hundred Tun, Such Seamen only excepted, for the time of their preſent Voyage only, as are already gone our of the River of <hi>Thames</hi> on Board any Ship or Veſſel bound to <hi>Newcaſtle, Sunderland,</hi> or Ports Adjacent, or are now on Board any Ship or Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel at this time Loaden and Bound from the ſaid Places or Ports to the Port of <hi>London.</hi> Our Intent being that ſuch and ſo many of the ſaid Seamen, as are not Abſolutely neceſſary for the Safety of ſuch Ship or Veſſel, ſhall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of their ſaid preſent Voyage, and at their now expected Arrival be liable to be Preſſed for Our Service. Provided always, That if any Colliers ſhall ſtay by the way. or make any Delays, in order to raiſe the Price of Coals, or ſhall put into any Port by the Way, unleſs for neceſſity, by reaſon of Tempeſt and unavoidable Peril of the Sea, this Exemption from Preſſing ſhall not be extended to them. And We do hereby make known to Our Loving Subjects, That for the Security of the Perſons and Ships bringing and conveying Coals, as aforeſaid, We have given effectual Order, that from time to time there ſhall be provided ſufficient Convoys for their ſafe Paſſage and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct to and from the Parts and Places aforeſaid. And Our Will and Pleaſure is, and We do hereby Declare, That if any Officers belonging to any Convoy imployed in this Service, ſhall neglect their Duty, or miſdemean them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they ſhall loſe their Places and Commands, and be further puniſhed according to their Demerits. And to the end that all convenient Expedition may be uſed in Diſcharging all Ships and Veſſels (that ſhall bring any Coals into the ſaid Port of <hi>London</hi>) in order to their returning and renewing their Voyages, We do Require and Command, That no ſuch Ship or Veſſel ſhall be above Ten Days in Vnlading, the ſaid Days to begin and be reckoned from the time of Coming into the Pool or Place of Vnlading. And We do hereby ſtrictly Charge and Command all Our Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Miniſters, and Subjects whatſoever, both by Sea and Land, That they take Notice of Our Royal Will and Pleaſure, publiſhed in this Our Proclamation, and give due Obedience thereunto at their Perils.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given at Our Court at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> 
                     <date>the Twenty third Day of <hi>April,</hi> 1691. In the Third Year of Our Reign.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſave King William and Queen Mary.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Charles Bill,</hi> and the Executrix of <hi>Thomas Newcomb,</hi> deceas'd; Printers to the King and Queens moſt Excellent Majeſties. 1691.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
